"Jó napot, pacák" Which, as somebody here must surely know,
Yo napot,pacak!'والتي يجب أن أعرفها بصفه شخصيه ,
means "What's up, guys?" in Magyar,
ما الآمرأيها الرفاق ؟" باللغة المجرية ,
that peculiar non-Indo-European language spoken by Hungarians
, اللغه المختصه بالمتحدثين من الهنغاريين بلغة أوروبيه غير هنديه
for which, given the fact that cognitive diversity is
الذي ,حدد حقيقة اداركنا للتقارب
at least as threatened as biodiversity on this planet,
الذي على الآقل يهدد التنوع البيولوجي على سطح هذا الكوكب ,
few would have imagined much of a future even a century or two ago.
الذي سوف يجسد أكثر في المستقبل حتى بعد قرن أو لقرنين قادمين .
But there it is: "Jó napot, pacák"
.لكن من هناك "Yo napot, pacak!"
I said somebody here must surely know, because
قلت أنه يجب أن يكون هناك شخص يعلم , لأنه
despite the fact that there aren't that many Hungarians to begin with,
بالرغم من حقيقة عدم وجود الكثير من الهنغاريين للبدأ ,
and the further fact that, so far as I know, there's not a drop
وحقيقه أخرى , التي أعلمها أنا حتى الآن , أنه لايوجد قطرة
of Hungarian blood in my veins, at every critical juncture of my life
دم هنغاريه تجري في عروقي ,عند كل منعطف هام في حياتي
there has been a Hungarian friend or mentor there beside me.
كان يوجد صديق هنغاري أو ناصح بجانبي .
I even have dreams that take place in landscapes
حتى تحققت أحلامي في االحقيقه
I recognize as the landscapes of Hungarian films,
أدركت المناظر الطبيعيه للآفلام الهنغاريه
especially the early movies of Miklos Jancso.
وخصوصا الافلام الأوائل ل ميكلوس جانسو
So, how do I explain this mysterious affinity?
كيف يمكن لي أن أشرح هذا التقارب الغامض ؟
Maybe it's because my native state of South Carolina,
ربما لآن بلدتي في جنوب كورلينا ,
which is not much smaller than present-day Hungary,
التي ليست أصغر من هنغاريا الآن بكثير ,
once imagined a future for itself as an independent country.
, سابقا كانت تحلم بمستقبل لنفسها كبلد مستقل .
And as a consequence of that presumption,
وفي تسلسل الآفتراضات هذا ,
my hometown was burned to the ground by an invading army,
بلدتي أحرقت وسويت بالآرض من قبل الجيش الغازي ,
an experience that has befallen many a Hungarian town and village
هذه التجربة كانت قد مرت بها الكثير من المدن والقرى الهنغاريه
throughout its long and troubled history.
خلال تاريخها الطويل والمليء بالمتاعب .
Or maybe it's because when I was a teenager back in the '50s,
أو ربما لآنني عندما كنت مراهقا في الخمسينات ,
my uncle Henry -- having denounced the Ku Klux Klan
من القرن الماضي , عمي هنري , كان قد ندد بالكو كلوكس كلان --
and been bombed for his trouble and had crosses burned in his yard,
وقصف لوقوعه في المتاعب وأحرقت الصلبان في باحة منزلة –
living under death threat -- took his wife and children to Massachusetts for safety
عاش تحت تهديد القتل ,أخذ زوجته وأولاده الى ماساشوستس ليكونوا بأمان
and went back to South Carolina to face down the Klan alone.
وعاد هو الى جنوب كرولينا ليواجه الكلان وحده .
That was a very Hungarian thing to do,
أنه أكثر الآشياء التي ممكن أن يفعلها الهنغاريون ,
as anyone will attest who remembers 1956.
كأي شخص يصدق من يتذكر1956.
And of course, from time to time Hungarians
وطبعا , من وقت لآخر الهنغاريون
have invented their own equivalent of the Klan.
يخترعون طرق تشبه الكلان
Well, it seems to me that this Hungarian presence in my life
حسنا , يبدو لي أن وجود هؤلاء الهنغاريين في حياتي
is difficult to account for, but ultimately I ascribe it to an admiration
يصعب عده , لكن في نهاية المطاف أعزو هذا الشيء الى أعجابي
for people with a complex moral awareness,
للآشخاص الذين يتمتعون بوعي أخلاقي معقد
with a heritage of guilt and defeat matched by defiance and bravado.
مع أرث للذنب والفشل مطابقة للجموح والتبجح
It's not a typical mindset for most Americans,
أنها ليست العقليه النموذجيه لكثير من الآمريكيين
but it is perforce typical of virtually all Hungarians.
لكنها بحكم الضروره نموذج للفضيله عند الهنغاريين .
So, "Jó napot, pacák!"
لذلك ,"Yo napot, pacak!"
I went back to South Carolina after some 15 years amid the alien corn
عدت أدراجي الى جنوب كرولينا بعد 15 عاما من وسط حقول الذرة الغريبه ,
at the tail end of the 1960s,
في أواخر 1960,
with the reckless condescension of that era
مع الانهيار المتهور لتلك الحقبة ,
thinking I would save my people.
فكرت أني أريد أن أنقذ شعبي .
Never mind the fact that they were slow to acknowledge they needed saving.
لاأهتم لحقيقة أنهم أبطئوا بمعرفة أنهم بحاجه لمن ينقذهم .
I labored in that vineyard for a quarter century before
عملت في حقل للعنب لمدة ربع قرن من قبل
making my way to a little kingdom of the just in upstate South Carolina,
أن أصنع طريقي للمملكة العدالة في ريف جنوب كارولينا ,
a Methodist-affiliated institution of higher learning called Wofford College.
المنتسبين الميثوديين لمؤسسة التعليم العالي تدعى جامعة ووفورد .
I knew nothing about Wofford
لم أكن أعلم شيئا عن ووفورد ,
and even less about Methodism,
وحتى على الاقل عن الميثودية ,
but I was reassured on the first day that I taught at Wofford College
ولكني كنت مطمئن منذ اليوم الآول الذي تعلمت فيه في ووفورد
to find, among the auditors in my classroom,
أني سأجده , في وسط الطلاب الموجودين في صفي
a 90-year-old Hungarian, surrounded by a bevy of middle-aged European women
رجل هنغاري في 90من عمره , محاط بسرب من نساء أوروبيات في منتصف العمر
who seemed to function as an entourage of Rhinemaidens.
اللآواتي بدين وكأنهن حاشية من العوانس .
He was a puckish widower whose wife and children were dead
كان أرمل شيطاني زوجته وابناؤه متوفيين
and whose grandchildren lived far away.
أحفاده يعيشون بعيدا عنه
In appearance, he resembled Mahatma Gandhi,
في شكله الخارجي يشبه مهاتما غاندي - -
minus the loincloth, plus orthopedic boots.
بسيط في الملبس ,زائد حذاء من العظم .
He had been born in 1903 in the provinces
ولد عام 1903في محافظات
of the old Austro-Hungarian Empire,
الامبراطورية النمساوية الهنغارية القديمة ,
in what later would become Yugoslavia.
والتي أصبحت لاحقا يوغوسلافيا .
He was ostracized as a child, not because he was a Jew --
كان منبوذا كطفل , ليس لآنه كان يهوديا –
his parents weren't very religious anyhow --
والداه لم يكونا متدينين على أي حال --
but because he had been born with two club feet,
لكن لآنه ولد مع قدمان روحاء ,
a condition which, in those days, required institutionalization
الحالة التي , في هذه الآيام ,تتطلب مؤسسات
and a succession of painful operations between the ages of one and 11.
وألم متواصل من العمليات من عمر السنه و عمر 11عاما
He went to the commercial business high school as a young man
ذهب الى المدرسة الثانوية التجارية كشاب
in Budapest, and there he was as smart as he was modest
في مدينة بودابست .هناك كان ذكيا كما كان متواضعا ,
and he enjoyed a considerable success. And after graduation
ولاقى نجاحا كبيرا , وبعد تخرجه ,
when he went into textile engineering, the success continued.
عندما ذهب الى هندسة الغزل والنسيج ,أستمر نجاحه .
He built one plant after another.
قام ببناء مصنع تلو الآخر .
He married and had two sons. He had friends in high places who
تزوج ولديه ولدان .لديه أصدقاء ذوي مناصب مرموقة
assured him that he was of great value to the economy.
الذين طمأنوه بأنه ذا قيمة عظيمه للآقتصاد
Once, as he had left instructions to have done,
في يوم من الآيام ,كان قد ترك تعليمات لتنفذ ,
he was summoned in the middle of the night by the night watchman at one of his plants.
استدعي في منتصف الليل من قبل الحارس الليلي في أحد المصانع .
The night watchman had caught an employee who was stealing socks --
كان قد امسك الحارس الليلي بموظف يقوم بسرقة الجوارب –
it was a hosiery mill, and he simply backed a truck up to the loading dock
كان مصنعا للجوارب ,وكان ببساطة يملك احتياطيا في شاحنة التحميل
and was shoveling in mountains of socks.
وكان التجريف في جبال من الجوارب.
Mr. Teszler went down to the plant and confronted the thief and said,
السيد تسزلر نزل اليه الى المصنع وواجه السارق وقال له ,
"But why do you steal from me? If you need money you have only to ask."
"لكن لماذا تقوم بسرقتي ؟ اذا كنت بحاجه للمال عليك فقط أن تطلب مني ."
The night watchman, seeing how things were going and waxing indignant,
الحارس الليلي , شاهد كيف جرت الامور و زال سخطه ,
said, "Well, we're going to call the police, aren't we?"
قال ,"حسنا , سوف نذهب لنبلغ الشرطه , الن نذهب ؟"
But Mr. Teszler answered, "No, that will not be necessary.
ولكن السيد تسيذلر أجاب ," لا,ليس ذلك ماسنفعله " .لن يكون ضروريا .
He will not steal from us again."
لن يسرق منا شيئا مجددا .
Well, maybe he was too trusting, because he stayed where he was
حسنا , ربما كان واثقا جدا ,لانه بقي
long after the Nazi Anschluss in Austria
فتره طويلة حيث كان بعد أن وصلت النازية الى النمسا ,
and even after the arrests and deportations began in Budapest.
حتى بعد القبض عليه وبدأ عمليات الترحيل في بودابست .
He took the simple precaution of having cyanide capsules placed in lockets
أخذ أحتياط بسيط بوضعه كبسولات من السينادي تضع في المناجد
that could be worn about the necks of himself and his family.
التي من الممكن أن يلبسها حول رقبته ورقبة عائلته
And then one day, it happened: he and his family were arrested
بعد ذلك ,في يوم من الآيام , حدث ذلك :ألقي القبض عليه وعلى عائلته
and they were taken to a death house on the Danube.
ومن ثم أخذوهم الى بيت الموت على نهر الدانوب.
In those early days of the Final Solution, it was handcrafted brutality;
في تلك الآيام الآولى للحل النهائي ,كان يستوحش بيديه --
people were beaten to death and their bodies tossed into the river.
اناس يضربون حتى الموت وتلقى جثثهم في النهر --
But none who entered that death house had ever come out alive.
لكن لا أحد قط دخل بيت الموت ثم عاد حياً.
And in a twist you would not believe in a Steven Spielberg film --
وفي تويست لن تصدق فيلم ستيفن سبيلبيرغ
the Gauleiter who was overseeing this brutal beating was the very same thief
قيادة جبهة العمل التي كانت تقوم بالآشراف على هذا الضرب الوحشي كانت تشبه السارق جدا
who had stolen socks from Mr. Teszler's hosiery mill.
الذي كان قد سرق الجوارب من مصنع جوارب السيد تسزلر
It was a brutal beating. And midway through that brutality,
كان ضربا وحشيا .وفي منتصف طريق تلك الوحشيه ,
one of Mr. Teszler's sons, Andrew, looked up and said,
واحد من أبناء تسزلر ,أندرو,نظر وقال ,
"Is it time to take the capsule now, Papa?"
هل حان وقت أخذ الكبسول , والدي ؟"
And the Gauleiter, who afterwards vanishes from this story,
وقيادة جبهة العمل, التي بعد ذلك تلاشت من القصه
leaned down and whispered into Mr. Teszler's ear,
أنحنى الى الاسفل وهمس في أذن السيد تسزلر ,
"No, do not take the capsule. Help is on the way."
لا , لا تأخذ الكبسول . المساعده في طريقها ."
And then resumed the beating.
وعاد لآستئناف الضرب .
But help was on the way, and shortly afterwards
ولكن المساعده -- المساعده في الطريق ,وبعد ذلك بفتره قصيرة
a car arrived from the Swiss Embassy.
وصلت سيارة من السفارة السويسرية
They were spirited to safety. They were reclassified as Yugoslav citizens
كان لديهم حماس للآمان . صنفوا على أنهم مواطنون يوغوسلافيون
and they managed to stay one step ahead of their pursuers
خططوا أن يكونوا خلف مطارديهم بخطوة
for the duration of the War, surviving burnings and bombings
خلال الحرب ,الناجون من الحرق والتفجيرات ,
and, at the end of the War, arrest by the Soviets.
و ,في نهاية الحرب ,أسر من قبل السوفييت
Probably, Mr. Teszler had gotten some money into Swiss bank accounts
ربما السيد تسزلر كان قد أودع مالا في حساب له في بنك سويسري
because he managed to take his family first to Great Britain,
لانه خطط لآخذ عائلته أولا الى بريطانيا العظمى ,
then to Long Island and then to the center of the textile industry in the American South.
ثم الى لونغ ايلاند ,وثم الى مركز مصانع الغزل والنسيج في جنوب أمريكا .
Which, as chance would have it, was Spartanburg, South Carolina,
الذي ,سيكون لديه فرصة ,كان سبارتونغ ,جنوب كارولينا :
the location of Wofford College.
موقع كلية ووفورد .
And there, Mr. Teszler began all over again and once again achieved immense success,
وبعد ذلك السيد تسزلر بدأ من جديد ,ومرة أخرى حقق نجاحا هائلا ,
especially after he invented the process
خاصة بعد أن أخترع عملية
for manufacturing a new fabric called double-knit.
لتصنيع نسيج جديد يسمى بالمزدوج المتماسك .
And then in the late 1950s, in the aftermath of Brown v. Board of Education,
وبعد ذلك -- بعد ذلك في أواخر عام 1950, في أعقاب مقابلة براون لمجلس التعليم ,
when the Klan was resurgent all over the South,
عندما أصبحت الكلان متعافية في جميع أنحاء الجنوب ,
Mr. Teszler said, "I have heard this talk before."
قال السيد تسزلر,"لقد سمعت هذا الحديث من قبل ."
And he called his top assistant to him and asked,
واستدعى مساعده وسأله ,
"Where would you say, in this region, racism is most virulent?"
أين تقولون ,في هذه المنطقه ,أن العنصريه أكثر فتكا ؟
"Well, I don't rightly know, Mr. Teszler. I reckon that would be Kings Mountain."
حسنا , لاأعلم , سيد تسزلر .أعتقد أنها سوف تكون في الكينغ ماونتن
"Good. Buy us some land in Kings Mountain
"جيد .أشتري لنا بعض الآراضي في الكينغ ماونتن ,
and announce we are going to build a major plant there."
ثم أعلن أننا سوف نقوم ببناء مصنع رئيسي هناك ."
The man did as he was told, and shortly afterwards,
فعل الرجل كما قيل له , وبعد فترة وجيزه
Mr. Teszler received a visit from the white mayor of Kings Mountain.
تلقى السيد تسزلر زيارة من عميد البيض في الكينغ ماونتن .
Now, you should know that at that time,
الآن ,يجب أن تعلموا هذا في ذلك الوقت
the textile industry in the South was notoriously segregated.
مصانع النسيج في الجنوب كانت معروفة أنها تفصل بين العرقين .
The white mayor visited Mr. Teszler and said,
عميد البيض زار السيد تسزلر وقال ,
"Mr. Teszler, I trust you’re going to be hiring a lot of white workers."
"سيد تسزلر ,أنا واثق انك ستقوم توظيف الكثير من العمال البيض ."
Mr. Teszler told him, "You bring me the best workers that you can find,
رد عليه السيد تسزلر,"أجلب لي أفضل العمال الذين تستطع إيجادهم ,
and if they are good enough, I will hire them."
وأذا كانوا جيدون بما يكفي, سوف أقوم بتوظيفهم ."
He also received a visit from the leader of the black community,
وتلقى زيارة أيضا من زعيم مجتمع السود,
a minister, who said, "Mr. Teszler, I sure hope you're going to
الوزير , الذي قال ," سيد تسزلر , أنا أأمل أنك سوف تقوم
hire some black workers for this new plant of yours."
بتوظيف عدد من العمال السود في مصنعك الجديد."
and if they are good enough, I will hire them."
وان كانوا جيدون بما يكفي , سوف أقوم بتوظيفهم ."
As it happens, the black minister did his job better than the white mayor,
وكما يحدث , وزير السود أدى عمله بطريقة أفضل من عمدة البيض ,
but that's neither here or there.
ولكن هذا لا هنا ولاهناك .
Mr. Teszler hired 16 men: eight white, eight black.
السيد تسزلر وظف 16 رجل , ثمانية من البيض ,وثمانية من السود .
They were to be his seed group, his future foremen.
كانوا سيكونون مجموعة جديده ,رجاله في المستقبل .
He had installed the heavy equipment for his new process
كان قد حمل معدات ثقيلة لعمليته الجديدة
in an abandoned store in the vicinity of Kings Mountain,
في المتجر المهجور على مقربة من كينغ ماونتن ,
and for two months these 16 men would live and work together,
وفي شهرين هؤلاء ال 16 رجل عاشوا وعملوا مع بعضهم البعض ,
mastering the new process.
يتقنون العمليه الجديده .
He gathered them together after an initial tour of that facility
قام بجمعهم بعد جولة أولية للمنشأة
and he asked if there were any questions.
وسالهم أن كان هناك أي سؤال .
There was hemming and hawing and shuffling of feet,
كان هناك هدب وتلعثم و فوضى بينهم ,
and then one of the white workers stepped forward and said,
ثم أحد العمال البيض تقدم للامام وقال ,
"Well, yeah. We’ve looked at this place and there's only one place to sleep,
"حسنا ,نعم .لقد ألقينا نظرة على المكان --ولايوجد غير مكان واحد للنوم ,
there's only one place to eat, there's only one bathroom,
مكان واحد للأكل , هناك حمام واحد ,
there's only one water fountain. Is this plant going to be integrated or what?"
لايوجد غير ينبوع واحد للشرب .هل سيكون هذا المصنع موحدا ,أم ماذا ؟"
Mr. Teszler said, "You are being paid twice the wages of any other textile workers in this region
قال السيد تسزلر,"أنت تأخذ ضعف الأجر لآي عامل نسيج أخر في هذه المنطقة ,
and this is how we do business. Do you have any other questions?"
وهذه هي الطريقه التي نعمل بها . هل لديك أسئلة أخرى ؟"
"No, I reckon I don't."
لا , أعتقد أنه ليس لدي ."
And two months later when the main plant opened
وبعد شهرين , عندما أفتتح المصنع الرئيسي
and hundreds of new workers, white and black,
ومئات من العاملين الجدد , بيض وسود ,
poured in to see the facility for the first time,
تدفقت لترى المنشأة للمرة الآولى ,
They toured the facility and were asked if there were any questions, and
تجولوا بالمنشأة وسئل أن كان أحد لديه سؤال . و
inevitably the same question arose:
حتما ,طرح نفس السؤال :
"Is this plant integrated or what?"
هل هذا المكان موحد , أم ماذا ؟"
And one of the white foremen stepped forward and said,
أحد العمال البيض المشرفين تقدم وقال ,
"You are being paid twice the wages of any other workers
أنت تأخذ ضعف أجرة العمال الآخرين
in this industry in this region and this is how we do business.
في هذا المصنع في هذه المنطقة وهذه هي الطريقة التي نؤدي بها أعمالنا .
Do you have any other questions?"
هل لديك أسئلة أخرى ؟"
And there were none. In one fell swoop,
هناك لم يجب أحد
Mr. Teszler had integrated the textile industry in that part of the South.
وحّد السيد تيسزلر صناعة الغزل والنسج في المنطقة الجنوبية
It was an achievement worthy of Mahatma Gandhi,
إنجاز أستحق أن يذكره المهاتما غاندي
conducted with the shrewdness of a lawyer and the idealism of a saint.
جرى بفطنة محامي ومثالية قديس
In his eighties, Mr. Teszler, having retired from the textile industry,
. في الثمانين من عمره تقاعد السيد تسزلر من صناعة النسيج
adopted Wofford College,
ليلتحق بكلية وفورد
auditing courses every semester,
لمراجعة المقررات لكل فصل
and because he had a tendency to kiss anything that moved,
ولعشقه لكل شيء يتحرك
becoming affectionately known as "Opi" -- which is Magyar for grandfather --
أصبح رسميا يعرف باسم مكتب التعليم العام -- وهو المجرية لجده --
by all and sundry. Before I got there, the library of the college
من قبل الجميع دون إستثناء . مع الوقت وصلت الى هناك , مكتبة الكلية
had been named for Mr. Teszler, and after I arrived in 1993,
كانت قد سميت باسم السيد تسزلر , بعد وصولي عام 1993
the faculty decided to honor itself by naming Mr. Teszler Professor of the College --
قرر أعضاء هيئة التدريس تشريف أنفسهم بتسمية السيد تسزلر كبروفسور للجامعة
partly because at that point he had already taken
ويرجع ذلك جزئيا في تلك المرحلة قد اتخذ بالفعل
all of the courses in the catalog, but mainly because
كل دروس السلسلة لكن في الأساس بسبب
he was so conspicuously wiser than any one of us.
كونه أحكم شخص فيما بيننا
To me, it was immensely reassuring that the presiding spirit
بالنسبة لي , كان من المطئن أكثر أن الروح القيادية
of this little Methodist college in upstate South Carolina
في كلية ميثودية صغيرة في ريف كارولينا الجنوبية
was a Holocaust survivor from Central Europe.
ناج من محرقة الهولوكوست من أوروبا الوسطى
Wise he was, indeed, but he also had a wonderful sense of humor.
كان حكيما , لكنه كان يمتلك أيضا حس فكاهي رائع
And once for an interdisciplinary class,
ومرة في صف التخصصات
I was screening the opening segment of Ingmar Bergman's "The Seventh Seal."
كنت اعرض مشاهد افتتاح فيلم العلامة السابعة لانجمار بيرجمان
As the medieval knight Antonius Block returns from the wild goose chase
كفارس من العصور الوسطى عاد انطونيوس بلوك من حملة ميؤوس منها
of the Crusades and arrives on the rocky shore of Sweden,
من الحروب الصليبية وصل الى شاطئ صخري في السويد
only to find the specter of death waiting for him,
ليجد شبح الموت بانتظاره
Mr. Teszler sat in the dark with his fellow students. And
كان السيد تسزلر جالس في الظلام مع طلابه
as death opened his cloak to embrace the knight
وفتح الموت عبائته ليحتضن الفارس
in a ghastly embrace, I heard Mr. Teszler's tremulous voice:
في احتضان مروع . سمعت صوت السيد تسزلر المرتعش
"Uh oh," he said, "This doesn't look so good." (Laughter)
قال "أوه أوه هذا لايبدو جيدا أبدا "
But it was music that was his greatest passion, especially opera.
لكن الموسيقى كانت شغفه الأعظم , خاصة الاوبرا
And on the first occasion that I visited his house, he gave me
وفي المناسبة الاولى التي زرت منزله بها أعطاني
honor of deciding what piece of music we would listen to.
شرف اختيار المقطوعة الموسيقية التي سنستمع اليها
And I delighted him by rejecting "Cavalleria Rusticana"
وأسعدته برفضي لـ "كافاليريا روستيكانا"
in favor of Bela Bartok's "Bluebeard's Castle."
لصالح "قلعة ذي اللحية الزرقاء" لـ بيلا بارتوك
I love Bartok's music, as did Mr. Teszler,
أحب موسيقى بارتوك مثل السيد تسزلر
and he had virtually every recording of Bartok's music ever issued.
عمليا كان لديه كل تسجيلات بارتوك الصادرة
And it was at his house that I heard for the first time
ومنزله كان المكان الذي استمتعت فيه للمرة الأولى
Mr. Teszler that it had been composed in nearby Asheville, North Carolina
السيد تسزلر أنها ألفت في أشفيل القريبة من كارولينا الشمالية
in the last year of the composer's life.
في آخر سنة من حياة المؤلف
He was dying of leukemia and he knew it,
مات بسرطان الدم وكان يعلم ذلك
and he dedicated this concerto to his wife,
قرر حينها إهداء تلك المقطوعة لزوجته
Dita, who was herself a concert pianist.
ديتا, التي كانت هي أيضا عازفة بيانو
And into the slow, second movement, marked "adagio religioso,"
وببطء الخطوة الثانية أسميت "أداغيو ريليجيوسو"
he incorporated the sounds of birdsong that he heard
ضمنها بأصوات تغريد الطيور التي سمعها
outside his window in what he knew would be his last spring;
خارج شباك غرفته فيما كان يعلم أنه آخر ربيع له
he was imagining a future for her in which he would play no part.
كان يتخيل حياتها المستقليه دونه
And clearly this composition is his final statement to her --
كان واضحا أن هذا التكوين هو كلامه الاخير لها
it was first performed after his death --
كان أول أداء لها بعد وفاته
and through her to the world.
ومن خلالها للعالم
And just as clearly, it is saying, "It's okay. It was all so beautiful.
كان جليا بأنه يقول " حسنا , كان كل شيء جميلا
Whenever you hear this, I will be there."
كلما استمعت اليها ,سأكون موجودا "
It was only after Mr. Teszler's death that I learned
فقط بعد وفاة السيد تسزلر علمت
that the marker on the grave of Bela Bartok in Hartsdale, New York
ان العلامة الموجودة على قبر بيلا بارتوك في هارتسدال في نيويورك
was paid for by Sandor Teszler. "Jó napot, Bela!"
دفعت من قبل ساندور تسزلر " مالامر , بيلا"
Not long before Mr. Teszler’s own death at the age of 97,
ليس كثيرا قبل وفاة السيد تسزلر في عمر الـ97
he heard me hold forth on human iniquity.
سمع مني باستمرار الحديث عن ظلم الانسان
I delivered a lecture in which I described history
قدمت محاضرة أصف فيها التاريخ ككل
as, on the whole, a tidal wave of human suffering and brutality,
كموجة عارمة من معاناة البشرية والوحشية
and Mr. Teszler came up to me afterwards with gentle reproach and said,
جائني بعد ذلك السيد تسزلر مع لوم لطيف وقال لي
"You know, Doctor, human beings are fundamentally good."
" أتعلم , دكتور , البشر أساسا جيدون "
And I made a vow to myself, then and there,
أخذت على نفسي عهدا , حينها وهناك
that if this man who had such cause to think otherwise
انه اذا كان هذا الشخص يملك أسبابا ليفكر بطريقة أخرى
had reached that conclusion,
قد وصل لهذه النتيجة
I would not presume to differ until he released me from my vow.
انا لن أفترض ان اختلف حتى يحررني من تعهدي
And now he's dead, so I'm stuck with my vow.
والان هو ميت لذا أنا متمسك بتعهدي
"Jó napot, Sandor!"
"مالامر ساندرو"
I thought my skein of Hungarian mentors had come to an end,
اعتقدت بلدي خصلة خيوط من الموجهين الهنغاريين قد حان لوضع النهاية
but almost immediately I met Francis Robicsek, a Hungarian doctor --
لكن على الفور التقيت بفرانسيس روبيكسيك, الطبيب الهنغاري --
actually a heart surgeon in Charlotte, North Carolina, then in his late seventies --
جراح القلب في شارلوت , كارولينا الشمالية , ثم في أواخر السبعينات من عمره
who had been a pioneer in open-heart surgery,
الذي كان رائدا في جراحة القلب المفتوح
and, tinkering away in his garage behind his house,
ويعبث بعيدا في مرآب سيارته خلف منزله
had invented many of the devices that are standard parts of those procedures.
حيث قد اخترع العديد من الأجهزة القياسية التي هي أجزاء من تلك الاجراءات
He's also a prodigious art collector, beginning as an intern in Budapest
هو أيضا جامع قطع فنية مذهل , حيث بدأ كمتدرب في بودابست
by collecting 16th- and 17th-century Dutch art and Hungarian painting,
من خلال جمع لوحات هولندية وهنغارية من القرن السادس عشر والسابع عشر
and when he came to this country moving on to Spanish colonial art,
وعندما قدم لهذه الدولة , اتجه للفن الاستعماري الإسباني
Russian icons and finally Mayan ceramics.
الرموز الروسية , وأخيرا خزفيات شعوب المايا
He's the author of seven books, six of them on Mayan ceramics.
هو كاتب لسبع كتب , ستة منهم عن خزفيات المايا
It was he who broke the Mayan codex, enabling scholars to relate
كان هو من فك رموز مخطوطات المايا , تمكن العلماء للربط
the pictographs on Mayan ceramics to the hieroglyphs of the Mayan script.
بين الكتابات المصورة في خزفيات المايا وبين الطلاسم المكتوبة
On the occasion of my first visit, we toured his house
بمناسبة زيارتي الاولى , ونحن بجولة في منزله
and we saw hundreds of works of museum quality,
شاهدنا المئات من الأعمال بجودة المتحف
and then we paused in front of a closed door and Dr. Robicsek said,
ثم توقفنا أمام الباب المغلق قال السيد روبيكسك
with obvious pride, "Now for the piece De resistance."
بفخر "الان الى قطعة من عصر النهضة "
And he opened the door and we walked into a
وفتح الباب , ومشينا الى
windowless 20-by-20-foot room with shelves from floor to ceiling, and
نوافذ 20 في 20 قدما غرف مع رفوف تمتد من الارض الى السقف
crammed on every shelf his collection of Mayan ceramics.
يزدحم كل رف بمجموعته من خزفيات المايا
Now, I know absolutely nothing about Mayan ceramics,
الان , أنا لا أعلم شيئا عن خزفيات المايا
but I wanted to be as ingratiating as possible so I said,
لكن أردت أن أتملق قدر الامكان . لذا قلت
"But Dr. Robicsek, this is absolutely dazzling."
" دكتور روبيكسيك, ان هذه المجموعة مبهرة جدا "
"Yes," he said. "That is what the Louvre said.
أجابني "تماما , هذا ما قاله متحف اللوفر أيضا
They would not leave me alone until I let them have a piece,
لم يدعني وشأني حتى أعطيته قطعه
but it was not a good one." (Laughter)
لكنها لم تكن فكرة جيدة
Well, it occurred to me that I should invite Dr. Robicsek
خطر لي أنه يجب أن أدعو الدكتور روبيكسيك
to lecture at Wofford College on -- what else?
ليحاضر في كلية ووفورد عن -- ماذا أيضا ؟
-- Leonardo da Vinci. And further, I should invite him to meet
ليوناردو دافنشي . وعلي أيضا أن أدعوه ليقابل
my oldest trustee, who had majored in French history at Yale
وصيي الأكبر سنا , الذي كان قد تخصص في التاريخ الفرنسي في جامعة ييل
some 70-odd years before and, at 89, still ruled the world's
قبل نحو سبعين عاما ونيف وفي عمر ال89 مازال يحكم في العالم
largest privately owned textile empire with an iron hand.
أكبر امبراطورية نسيج مملوكة من قبل القطاع الخاص بقبضة من حديد
His name is Roger Milliken. And Mr. Milliken agreed,
اسمه روجر ميليكان . وافق السيد ميليكان
and Dr. Robicsek agreed. And Dr. Robicsek visited
ووافق الدكتور روبيكسيك أيضا . وتمت زيارة الدكتور روبيكسيك
and delivered the lecture and it was a dazzling success.
وألقى المحاضرة التي حققت نجاحا باهرا
And afterwards we convened at the President's House with Dr. Robicsek
وبعد ذلك إجتمعنا في منزل الرئيس مع الدكتور روبيكسيك
on one hand, Mr. Milliken on the other.
من ناحية السيد ميليكان ومن ناحية أخرى
And it was only at that moment, as we were sitting down to dinner,
وفي تلك اللحظة عندما جلسنا على العشاء
that I recognized the enormity of the risk I had created,
أدركت حجم الخطر الذي أوجدته
together -- it was like introducing Mothra to Godzilla over the skyline of Tokyo.
كان كتقديم موثرا لغودزيلا في سماء طوكيو
If they didn't like each other, we could all get trampled to death.
ان لم يعجب أحدهما بالاخر , سندهس جميعا حتى الموت
But they did, they did like each other.
لكنهما فعلاها . أعجب أحدهما بالاخر
They got along famously until the very end of the meal,
استرجعوا ذكريات الشهرة -- حتى اللحظة الاخيرة من الوجبة
and then they got into a furious argument.
ليدخلوا بعدها في نقاش عنيف
And what they were arguing about was this:
وماكانا يتناقشان حوله هو :
whether the second Harry Potter movie was as good as the first. (Laughter)
ما إذا كان الجزء الثاني من فيلم هاري بوتر بجودة الجزء الاول أم لا
Mr. Milliken said it was not. Dr. Robicsek disagreed.
السيد ميليكان كان يقول لا والدكتور روبيكسيك كان يخالفه
I was still trying to take in the notion that these titans,
كنت مازلت مأخوذ بالفكرة التي تقول بأنهم من الجبابرة
these masters of the universe, in their spare time watch Harry Potter movies,
سادات الكون في أوقات فراغهم يشاهدون أفلام هاري بوتر
"You just think it's so good because you didn't read the book."
" أنت تعتقد بأنه جيد جدا لأنك لم تقرأ الكتاب "
And Dr. Robicsek reeled back in his chair, but quickly gathered his wits,
ترنح السيد روبيكسيك في مقعده للوراء لكنه استجمع ذكائه سريعا
leaned forward and said, "Well, that is true, but I'll bet you went
وانحنى للأمام ليقول " حسنا , هذا صحيح , لكن أراهن أنك ذهبت
to the movie with a grandchild." "Well, yes, I did," conceded Mr. Milliken.
لمشاهدة الفيلم مع أحفادك " " حسنا , أجل, فعلت " أعترف السيد ميليكان
"Aha!" said Dr. Robicsek. "I went to the movie all by myself." (Laughter) (Applause)
" اها " رد السيد روبيكسيك " أنا ذهبت لمشاهدة الفيلم لوحدي"
And I realized, in this moment of revelation,
وأدركت في تلك اللحظة من الاظهار
that what these two men were revealing was the secret
أن هاذان الرجلان يفشيان سرا
of their extraordinary success, each in his own right.
من أسرار نجاحهما الاستثننائي , كل في مجاله
And it lay precisely in that insatiable curiosity,
وتكمن بالضبط في نهم الفضول
that irrepressible desire to know, no matter what the subject,
الرغبة اللامحدودة للمعرفة -- لايهم الموضوع
no matter what the cost,
لاتهم التكلفة
even at a time when the keepers of the Doomsday Clock
حتى عندما يرغب حماة يوم القيامة
are willing to bet even money that the human race won't be around
المراهنة بالمال حتى الجنس البشري لن يكون موجودا
to imagine anything in the year 2100, a scant 93 years from now.
تخيل أي شي في عام 2100 , 93 سنة شحيحة من الان
"Live each day as if it is your last," said Mahatma Gandhi.
" عش كل يوم كأنه آخر يوم لك " قال مهاتما غاندي
"Learn as if you'll live forever."
" تعلم كأنك ستعيش أبدا "
This is what I'm passionate about. It is precisely this.
هذا ما أنا شغوف به تماما
It is this inextinguishable, undaunted appetite for learning and experience,
هذا شيء صعب إخماده , شهية واسعة للتعلم والخبرة
no matter how risible, no matter how esoteric,
لايهم كم هو مضحك , لايهم كم هو سري
no matter how seditious it might seem.
لايهم كم يبدو فاتنا
This defines the imagined futures of our fellow Hungarians --
هذا التعريف لنتخيل مستقبل إخواننا الهنغاريين
Robicsek, Teszler and Bartok -- as it does my own.
روبيكسيك وتسزلروباتروك , كما فعلوا بي
As it does, I suspect, that of everybody here.
كما فعلوا -اعتقد - بكل شخص هنا
To which I need only add, "Ez a mi munkank; es nem is keves."
أحتاج فقط أن أضيف "Ez a mi munkank; es nem is keves."
This is our task; we know it will be hard.
هذه مهمتنا . نعلم أنها ستكون صعبة
"Ez a mi munkank; es nem is keves. Jó napot, pacák!" (Applause)
"هذا هو عملنا ، وليس مجرد أمثلة قليلة." Yo napot, pacak!